<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<workflows-reference preset="ddd-solid-bdd">
  <purpose>Provide Domain-Driven Design plus SOLID plus BDD/TDD workflows for Compass tasks.</purpose>

  <documentation-context>
    <rule>Read docs/decisions/0001-orientation-lock.md first.</rule>
    <rule>Read docs/architecture/domain-driven-design.md and docs/architecture/bounded-context-structure.md before design or implementation.</rule>
    <rule>Read docs/foundation/domain-modeling-principles.md before naming domain concepts or creating abstractions.</rule>
    <rule>Read docs/process/bdd-tdd-workflow.md before selecting examples and tests.</rule>
    <rule>Read relevant docs/modules notes for the bounded context or domain capability.</rule>
  </documentation-context>

  <workflow type="new_feature">
    <description>Add one business capability by clarifying language, context, examples, model, and tests before implementation.</description>
    <enforcement>
      <rule>Run phases sequentially: language discovery, context design, implementation.</rule>
      <rule>Execute exactly one bounded-context behavior per workflow.</rule>
      <rule>BDD examples must clarify behavior before technical TDD begins.</rule>
      <rule>Do not place behavior in a context until ownership and language are explicit.</rule>
      <rule>Implementation must stop after each verified domain/application/adapter checkpoint.</rule>
    </enforcement>
    <phase name="language-discovery" gate="developer_approval_required">
      <purpose>Align ubiquitous language and behavior examples before designing code.</purpose>
      <actions>
        <action>Read DDD architecture, bounded-context structure, domain modeling, and BDD/TDD docs.</action>
        <action>Identify the business capability and candidate bounded context.</action>
        <action>List domain terms, definitions, ambiguous words, and rejected meanings.</action>
        <action>Write Given/When/Then behavior examples for happy, common, and important failure paths.</action>
        <action>Split behaviors owned by other contexts into pending work.</action>
      </actions>
      <phase-output>
        <ubiquitous-language>Terms and definitions.</ubiquitous-language>
        <bounded-context>Owning context and integration assumptions.</bounded-context>
        <behavior-examples>Given/When/Then scenarios.</behavior-examples>
        <open-questions>Questions that affect model ownership.</open-questions>
      </phase-output>
    </phase>
    <phase name="context-design" gate="developer_approval_required">
      <purpose>Design the domain model, application use case, and behavior-test matrix inside the bounded context.</purpose>
      <actions>
        <action>Choose the bounded context folder from docs/architecture/bounded-context-structure.md.</action>
        <action>Define aggregate, entity, value object, domain service, domain event, and invariant candidates.</action>
        <action>Define application use case input, output, business errors, and consumer-owned ports.</action>
        <action>Apply SOLID at domain and application boundaries.</action>
        <action>Map BDD examples to TDD levels: domain, application, adapter, or integration.</action>
        <action>Mark examples selected, rejected, or postponed.</action>
      </actions>
      <phase-output>
        <domain-model>Aggregates, values, invariants, policies, and events.</domain-model>
        <application-contract>Use case, inputs, outputs, errors, and ports.</application-contract>
        <bdd-tdd-matrix>Examples mapped to test levels.</bdd-tdd-matrix>
        <docs-impact>Context map, module note, or decision updates.</docs-impact>
      </phase-output>
    </phase>
    <phase name="implementation" gate="manual_checkpoint_required">
      <purpose>Implement approved DDD behavior through domain, application, and adapter checkpoints.</purpose>
      <actions>
        <action>Start with domain behavior or application use case tests from approved examples.</action>
        <action>Implement domain model and application orchestration before adapters unless approved otherwise.</action>
        <action>Keep dependencies inward and interfaces consumer-owned.</action>
        <action>Add adapters only after domain and application behavior are protected.</action>
        <action>Stop after each checkpoint and ask before continuing.</action>
      </actions>
      <phase-output>
        <current-checkpoint>Domain, application, or adapter checkpoint implemented.</current-checkpoint>
        <changed-files>Files changed.</changed-files>
        <verification>Commands run and results.</verification>
        <context-impact>Bounded context or integration impact.</context-impact>
      </phase-output>
    </phase>
    <evidence>Approved language, approved context design, BDD examples, TDD verification, and docs update when domain ownership changes.</evidence>
  </workflow>

  <workflow type="feature_update">
    <steps>
      <step order="1">Find the owning bounded context and current ubiquitous language.</step>
      <step order="2">Add or update Given/When/Then examples for changed behavior.</step>
      <step order="3">Map examples to domain, application, adapter, or integration tests.</step>
      <step order="4">Change the model or use case in the smallest owning context.</step>
      <step order="5">Update context/module docs if language or ownership changed.</step>
    </steps>
    <evidence>Updated examples, tests, and context docs if needed.</evidence>
  </workflow>

  <workflow type="bug_fix">
    <steps>
      <step order="1">Reproduce the bug as a business behavior example.</step>
      <step order="2">Identify the bounded context and invariant or policy that failed.</step>
      <step order="3">Add a failing regression test at the proper DDD level.</step>
      <step order="4">Fix the smallest domain/application/adapter cause.</step>
      <step order="5">Run affected context tests and broader integration tests when contracts changed.</step>
    </steps>
    <evidence>Behavior example, regression test, bounded-context fix, and verification.</evidence>
  </workflow>

  <workflow type="architecture_change">
    <steps>
      <step order="1">Identify whether the change affects context boundaries, aggregate ownership, integration contracts, or dependency direction.</step>
      <step order="2">Compare 2-3 context or model options and trade-offs.</step>
      <step order="3">Update context map, architecture docs, or decision records before implementation.</step>
      <step order="4">Implement one context or integration change at a time.</step>
      <step order="5">Verify context tests and integration contracts.</step>
    </steps>
    <evidence>Updated DDD docs, context/integration tests, and dependency-boundary review.</evidence>
  </workflow>
</workflows-reference>
