<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<workflows-reference preset="ddd-solid-bdd">
  <purpose>Provide Domain-Driven Design plus SOLID plus BDD/TDD workflows for Compass tasks.</purpose>

  <documentation-context>
    <rule>Read docs/decisions/0001-orientation-lock.md first.</rule>
    <rule>Read docs/architecture/domain-driven-design.md and docs/architecture/bounded-context-structure.md before design or implementation.</rule>
    <rule>Read docs/foundation/domain-modeling-principles.md before naming domain concepts or creating abstractions.</rule>
    <rule>Read docs/process/bdd-tdd-workflow.md before selecting examples and tests.</rule>
    <rule>Read relevant docs/modules notes for the bounded context or domain capability.</rule>
  </documentation-context>

  <task-memory-gate>
    <rule>For long or risky work with at least two concrete implementation slices after alignment or design, load Compass references/task-memory.xml.</rule>
    <rule>Implementation may not start until the task memory outcome is reported as created, resumed, or not-required.</rule>
    <rule>When task memory is required, docs/.tasks/&lt;task&gt;/goal.md, diagram.md, and memories.md must exist before the first implementation edit or command.</rule>
    <rule>Missing docs/_templates task memory files are a documentation gap, not permission to skip this gate.</rule>
  </task-memory-gate>

  <workflow type="new_feature">
    <description>Add one business capability by clarifying language, context, examples, model, and tests before implementation.</description>
    <enforcement>
      <rule>Run phases sequentially: language discovery, context design, implementation.</rule>
      <rule>Execute exactly one bounded-context behavior per workflow.</rule>
      <rule>BDD examples must clarify behavior before technical TDD begins.</rule>
      <rule>Do not place behavior in a context until ownership and language are explicit.</rule>
      <rule>Implementation must stop after each verified domain/application/adapter checkpoint.</rule>
      <rule>Before implementation starts, satisfy the task-memory-gate for any long or risky multi-slice feature.</rule>
    </enforcement>
    <phase name="language-discovery" gate="developer_approval_required">
      <purpose>Align ubiquitous language and behavior examples before designing code.</purpose>
      <actions>
        <action>Read DDD architecture, bounded-context structure, domain modeling, and BDD/TDD docs.</action>
        <action>Identify the business capability and candidate bounded context.</action>
        <action>List domain terms, definitions, ambiguous words, and rejected meanings.</action>
        <action>Write Given/When/Then behavior examples for happy, common, and important failure paths.</action>
        <action>Split behaviors owned by other contexts into pending work.</action>
      </actions>
      <phase-output>
        <ubiquitous-language>Terms and definitions.</ubiquitous-language>
        <bounded-context>Owning context and integration assumptions.</bounded-context>
        <behavior-examples>Given/When/Then scenarios.</behavior-examples>
        <open-questions>Questions that affect model ownership.</open-questions>
      </phase-output>
    </phase>
    <phase name="context-design" gate="developer_approval_required">
      <purpose>Design the domain model, application use case, and behavior-test matrix inside the bounded context.</purpose>
      <actions>
        <action>Choose the bounded context folder from docs/architecture/bounded-context-structure.md.</action>
        <action>Define aggregate, entity, value object, domain service, domain event, and invariant candidates.</action>
        <action>Define application use case input, output, business errors, and consumer-owned ports.</action>
        <action>Apply SOLID at domain and application boundaries.</action>
        <action>Map BDD examples to TDD levels: domain, application, adapter, or integration.</action>
        <action>Mark examples selected, rejected, or postponed.</action>
      </actions>
      <phase-output>
        <domain-model>Aggregates, values, invariants, policies, and events.</domain-model>
        <application-contract>Use case, inputs, outputs, errors, and ports.</application-contract>
        <bdd-tdd-matrix>Examples mapped to test levels.</bdd-tdd-matrix>
        <docs-impact>Context map, module note, or decision updates.</docs-impact>
      </phase-output>
    </phase>
    <phase name="implementation" gate="manual_checkpoint_required">
      <purpose>Implement approved DDD behavior through domain, application, and adapter checkpoints.</purpose>
      <actions>
        <action>Before the first implementation edit or command, report the task memory outcome: created, resumed, or not-required.</action>
        <action>Start with domain behavior or application use case tests from approved examples.</action>
        <action>Implement domain model and application orchestration before adapters unless approved otherwise.</action>
        <action>Keep dependencies inward and interfaces consumer-owned.</action>
        <action>Add adapters only after domain and application behavior are protected.</action>
        <action>Stop after each checkpoint and ask before continuing.</action>
      </actions>
      <phase-output>
        <current-checkpoint>Domain, application, or adapter checkpoint implemented.</current-checkpoint>
        <changed-files>Files changed.</changed-files>
        <verification>Commands run and results.</verification>
        <context-impact>Bounded context or integration impact.</context-impact>
      </phase-output>
    </phase>
    <evidence>Approved language, approved context design, BDD examples, TDD verification, and docs update when domain ownership changes.</evidence>
  </workflow>

  <workflow type="feature_update">
    <description>Change existing domain behavior by controlling the delta from protected bounded-context behavior.</description>
    <enforcement>
      <rule>Run phases sequentially: baseline-discovery, delta-design, implementation-checkpoints, and rollout-cleanup when rollout guards or compatibility paths are introduced.</rule>
      <rule>Classify as architecture_change first when the update changes bounded-context ownership, aggregate ownership, integration contracts, or dependency direction.</rule>
      <rule>Before implementation starts, satisfy the task-memory-gate for any long, risky, or multi-slice update.</rule>
      <rule>Use ubiquitous language consistently and do not duplicate another context's rule locally.</rule>
      <rule>High-risk updates must define rollback, feature-flag, dark-launch, compatibility, or cleanup evidence before implementation.</rule>
    </enforcement>
    <phase name="baseline-discovery" gate="developer_approval_required">
      <purpose>Protect current domain language, examples, and context ownership before deciding what may change.</purpose>
      <actions>
        <action>Find the owning bounded context, aggregate or use case, current ubiquitous language, examples, tests, docs, commands, and integration points.</action>
        <action>State current domain behavior, invariants, policies, integration contracts, and expectations that must remain stable.</action>
        <action>Classify update risk as minor, medium, or high based on blast radius, reversibility, data impact, user visibility, and context-boundary impact.</action>
        <action>Record ambiguity before designing the delta.</action>
      </actions>
      <phase-output>
        <baseline>Owning context, language, behavior examples, tests, docs, and verification commands observed.</baseline>
        <preserve-list>Behavior, language, invariants, contracts, and non-goals that must not drift.</preserve-list>
        <risk-level>minor, medium, or high with reason.</risk-level>
        <ambiguity>Conflicts or unknowns.</ambiguity>
      </phase-output>
    </phase>
    <phase name="delta-design" gate="developer_approval_required">
      <purpose>Define the exact domain behavior change and executable examples before editing.</purpose>
      <actions>
        <action>State old behavior, new behavior, unchanged behavior, and intentionally removed behavior if any.</action>
        <action>Add or update Given/When/Then examples for preserved and changed behavior.</action>
        <action>Map examples to domain, application, adapter, or integration tests at the cheapest sufficient level.</action>
        <action>Define the smallest owning context, aggregate, policy, use case, or adapter to change.</action>
        <action>Decide whether the update needs a feature flag, dark launch, compatibility path, rollback plan, monitoring, docs update, or decision record.</action>
        <action>Define the implementation slices and verification command for each slice.</action>
      </actions>
      <phase-output>
        <delta>Approved behavior change and unchanged behavior.</delta>
        <examples>Updated behavior examples and test mapping.</examples>
        <slices>Ordered implementation checkpoints.</slices>
        <rollout-risk>Flag, rollback, monitoring, compatibility, cleanup, or not needed.</rollout-risk>
        <docs-impact>Context docs, language docs, decisions, or none.</docs-impact>
      </phase-output>
    </phase>
    <phase name="implementation-checkpoints" gate="manual_checkpoint_required">
      <purpose>Apply one approved delta slice inside the owning context.</purpose>
      <actions>
        <action>Before the first implementation edit or command, report the task memory outcome: created, resumed, or not-required.</action>
        <action>Add or update the approved examples and tests for the current slice when practical.</action>
        <action>Change the smallest owning domain model, application use case, adapter, or integration point and avoid introducing competing language.</action>
        <action>Run the current slice verification command.</action>
        <action>Stop after each verified slice and ask before continuing.</action>
      </actions>
      <phase-output>
        <current-slice>Delta slice implemented.</current-slice>
        <baseline-protection>Example or regression evidence added or reused.</baseline-protection>
        <changed-files>Files changed.</changed-files>
        <verification>Commands run and results.</verification>
        <context-impact>Bounded context or integration impact.</context-impact>
        <remaining-risk>Known gaps or follow-up work.</remaining-risk>
      </phase-output>
    </phase>
    <phase name="rollout-cleanup" gate="manual_checkpoint_required">
      <purpose>Close temporary risk controls introduced for the update.</purpose>
      <actions>
        <action>Record feature flag, dark launch, compatibility path, monitoring, rollback, or cleanup status when any were introduced.</action>
        <action>Remove stale flags or inactive compatibility paths after the update is fully accepted.</action>
        <action>Update context docs, decisions, public contracts, or runbooks when behavior or rollout expectations changed.</action>
        <action>Run final verification for the touched scope.</action>
      </actions>
      <phase-output>
        <rollout-state>Flag, rollout, compatibility, rollback, or cleanup state.</rollout-state>
        <docs-updated>Docs changed or intentionally unchanged.</docs-updated>
        <verification>Commands run and results.</verification>
      </phase-output>
    </phase>
    <evidence>Approved baseline, approved delta design, updated examples, regression coverage for preserved behavior, changed-behavior verification, slice checkpoints, and rollout or cleanup evidence when needed.</evidence>
  </workflow>

  <workflow type="bug_fix">
    <steps>
      <step order="1">Reproduce the bug as a business behavior example.</step>
      <step order="2">Identify the bounded context and invariant or policy that failed.</step>
      <step order="3">Add a failing regression test at the proper DDD level.</step>
      <step order="4">Fix the smallest domain/application/adapter cause.</step>
      <step order="5">Run affected context tests and broader integration tests when contracts changed.</step>
    </steps>
    <evidence>Behavior example, regression test, bounded-context fix, and verification.</evidence>
  </workflow>

  <workflow type="architecture_change">
    <steps>
      <step order="1">Identify whether the change affects context boundaries, aggregate ownership, integration contracts, or dependency direction.</step>
      <step order="2">Compare 2-3 context or model options and trade-offs.</step>
      <step order="3">Update context map, architecture docs, or decision records before implementation.</step>
      <step order="4">Implement one context or integration change at a time.</step>
      <step order="5">Verify context tests and integration contracts.</step>
    </steps>
    <evidence>Updated DDD docs, context/integration tests, and dependency-boundary review.</evidence>
  </workflow>
</workflows-reference>
