<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<classification-reference>
  <purpose>Classify by the workflow and risk needed, not only by the user's words.</purpose>

  <decision-tree>
    <question order="1" type-if-yes="hotfix_incident">Is production currently degraded, blocked, or urgent?</question>
    <question order="2" type-if-yes="research_spike">Is the main goal to discover feasibility, compare options, or investigate without a committed implementation?</question>
    <question order="3" type-if-yes="architecture_change">Does the task alter architecture boundaries, dependency direction, module structure, shared kernel concepts, platform categories, or cross-module contracts?</question>
    <question order="4" type-if-yes="db_migration">Does it change database schema, migrations, indexes, constraints, seed data, or persistence ownership?</question>
    <question order="5" type-if-yes="new_feature">Does it add user-visible or business behavior that did not exist?</question>
    <question order="6" type-if-yes="feature_update">Does it intentionally change existing behavior?</question>
    <question order="7" type-if-yes="bug_fix">Does it restore expected behavior after a defect?</question>
    <question order="8" type-if-yes="refactor">Does it change internal structure without intended behavior change?</question>
    <question order="9" type-if-yes="performance">Does it improve latency, throughput, memory, query cost, or resource usage?</question>
    <question order="10" type-if-yes="security">Does it address auth, authorization, secrets, injection, data exposure, crypto, dependency vulnerability, or abuse prevention?</question>
    <question order="11" type-if-yes="dependency_update">Does it update libraries, runtimes, generated clients, or lockfiles?</question>
    <question order="12" type-if-yes="build_ci_tooling">Does it change build scripts, CI, local tooling, codegen commands, linters, or developer automation?</question>
    <question order="13" type-if-yes="docs_only">Is it only documentation, comments, diagrams, onboarding, or specifications?</question>
    <question order="14" type-if-yes="test_only">Is it only tests or test infrastructure without production behavior change?</question>
    <question order="15" type-if-yes="cleanup_chore">Is it small maintenance with no behavior or architecture intent?</question>
    <question order="16" type-if-yes="release_deploy">Is it release, versioning, changelog, tagging, packaging, or deployment preparation?</question>
  </decision-tree>

  <routing-clarifications>
    <rule>Existing module, feature folder, screen, or component ownership is placement evidence only; it does not by itself make the task a feature_update.</rule>
    <rule>Adding a new use case, capability, user action, endpoint, screen flow, integration path, or business workflow inside an existing module is new_feature unless the dominant risk is architecture_change, db_migration, security, or hotfix_incident.</rule>
    <rule>Use feature_update only when the same use case or behavior already exists and the task intentionally changes its expected behavior, contract, rule, or output.</rule>
    <example request="Add Google Sign-In to the existing login feature" type="new_feature">Google Sign-In is a new login use case and capability; the existing login module only tells Compass where the feature belongs.</example>
  </routing-clarifications>

  <tie-breakers>
    <rule>Architecture beats feature: if a feature requires a new boundary, classify as architecture_change with new_feature secondary.</rule>
    <rule>Incident beats bug: if users or production are currently affected, classify as hotfix_incident.</rule>
    <rule>Security beats normal fix: if exploitability or data exposure is involved, classify as security.</rule>
    <rule>Migration is often secondary: pair db_migration with the behavior task unless schema work is the whole request.</rule>
    <rule>Refactor must not change behavior. If behavior changes, it is not only refactor.</rule>
    <rule>Docs-only must not modify production behavior.</rule>
  </tie-breakers>

  <clarifying-questions max-per-turn="1">
    <question>Is production currently impacted, or is this normal backlog work?</question>
    <question>Should this change user-visible behavior, or only internal structure?</question>
    <question>Does this require database schema or migration changes?</question>
    <question>Is the goal to implement, or only investigate and recommend?</question>
    <question>Does this touch module boundaries or dependency direction?</question>
  </clarifying-questions>
</classification-reference>
