<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<workflows-reference preset="research-based">
  <purpose>Provide workflows for selecting and applying an evidence-based architecture orientation.</purpose>

  <documentation-context>
    <rule>Read docs/decisions/0001-orientation-lock.md first.</rule>
    <rule>Read docs/architecture/research-based-architecture.md, docs/foundation/researched-principles.md, and docs/process/researched-workflow.md before planning.</rule>
    <rule>Use current primary or authoritative sources when the selected direction is not yet locked.</rule>
    <rule>Cite sources in decision docs before implementation depends on the researched choice.</rule>
  </documentation-context>

  <task-memory-gate>
    <rule>For long or risky work with at least two concrete implementation slices after alignment or design, load Compass references/task-memory.xml.</rule>
    <rule>Implementation may not start until the task memory outcome is reported as created, resumed, or not-required.</rule>
    <rule>When task memory is required, docs/.tasks/&lt;task&gt;/goal.md, diagram.md, and memories.md must exist before the first implementation edit or command.</rule>
    <rule>Missing docs/_templates task memory files are a documentation gap, not permission to skip this gate.</rule>
  </task-memory-gate>

  <workflow type="new_feature">
    <description>Add one capability only after research has selected the architecture, principles, and workflow to apply.</description>
    <enforcement>
      <rule>Run phases sequentially: research lock, design, implementation.</rule>
      <rule>Do not implement feature code until the researched orientation is selected and recorded.</rule>
      <rule>Research must compare at least three viable combinations when the direction is unknown.</rule>
      <rule>Implementation follows the workflow recorded by the research decision.</rule>
      <rule>Before implementation starts, satisfy the task-memory-gate for any long or risky multi-slice feature.</rule>
    </enforcement>
    <phase name="research-lock" gate="developer_approval_required">
      <purpose>Select the orientation from current evidence before feature design.</purpose>
      <actions>
        <action>Read existing docs and inspect the codebase.</action>
        <action>Browse current primary or authoritative sources for architecture, principles, and workflow options.</action>
        <action>Compare at least three viable combinations.</action>
        <action>Recommend one direction with trade-offs and source links.</action>
        <action>Update research-based architecture, principles, workflow, and decision docs after approval.</action>
      </actions>
      <phase-output>
        <options>Compared architecture/principle/workflow combinations.</options>
        <recommendation>Selected direction and rationale.</recommendation>
        <sources>Authoritative source links.</sources>
        <trade-offs>Accepted costs and rejected options.</trade-offs>
      </phase-output>
    </phase>
    <phase name="design" gate="developer_approval_required">
      <purpose>Design the feature according to the approved researched orientation.</purpose>
      <actions>
        <action>Translate the researched orientation into concrete boundaries, tests, and docs for the selected feature.</action>
        <action>Define behavior contract, ownership, data flow, and verification strategy.</action>
        <action>Mark behavior selected, rejected, or postponed.</action>
      </actions>
      <phase-output>
        <orientation-application>How the researched direction shapes this feature.</orientation-application>
        <behavior-test-matrix>Scenarios and verification levels.</behavior-test-matrix>
        <docs-impact>Docs or decisions to update.</docs-impact>
      </phase-output>
    </phase>
    <phase name="implementation" gate="manual_checkpoint_required">
      <purpose>Implement the approved feature under the researched orientation.</purpose>
      <actions>
        <action>Before the first implementation edit or command, report the task memory outcome: created, resumed, or not-required.</action>
        <action>Follow the approved researched workflow.</action>
        <action>Implement one verified slice at a time.</action>
        <action>Verify behavior and any assumptions from the researched architecture.</action>
        <action>Stop after each checkpoint.</action>
      </actions>
      <phase-output>
        <current-slice>Slice implemented.</current-slice>
        <changed-files>Files changed.</changed-files>
        <verification>Commands run and results.</verification>
        <research-assumptions>Assumptions verified or still risky.</research-assumptions>
      </phase-output>
    </phase>
    <evidence>Approved research lock, cited sources, approved design, and implementation verification.</evidence>
  </workflow>

  <workflow type="research_spike">
    <steps>
      <step order="1">State the research question and decision to be unlocked.</step>
      <step order="2">Gather current primary or authoritative sources.</step>
      <step order="3">Compare at least three options when selecting orientation.</step>
      <step order="4">Recommend one option with trade-offs.</step>
      <step order="5">Update research docs or decision records when the user approves.</step>
    </steps>
    <evidence>Sources, comparison, recommendation, and documented trade-offs.</evidence>
  </workflow>
</workflows-reference>
