<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<workflows-reference preset="clean-solid-tdd">
  <purpose
    >Provide Clean Architecture plus SOLID plus TDD workflows for Compass tasks.</purpose>

  <documentation-context>
    <rule
        >For every Compass-guided task, read the target project's available docs before planning or editing.</rule>
    <rule
        >Use docs/decisions/0001-orientation-lock.md as the default architecture, principles, and workflow lock when it exists.</rule>
    <rule
        >Read architecture, foundation, and process docs linked by the orientation lock before designing packages, tests, boundaries, or implementation flow.</rule>
    <rule
        >Read relevant docs/modules notes before touching a module, domain, feature area, bounded context, or slice.</rule>
    <rule
        >Read relevant docs/decisions records before changing boundaries, dependencies, data ownership, contracts, build flow, or release flow.</rule>
    <rule
        >Read docs/reference when changing schemas, public contracts, naming rules, note structure, or orientation presets.</rule>
    <rule
        >Do not require AGENTS.md to link or duplicate Compass docs; AGENTS.md is repository instruction context only when present.</rule>
    <rule
        >If relevant docs are missing, continue with the best available evidence and report the documentation gap.</rule>
    <rule
        >If clean-solid-tdd docs were just bootstrapped, adapt Go-oriented reference examples to the target language or stack before using them as project rules.</rule>
  </documentation-context>

  <task-memory-gate>
    <rule
        >For long or risky work with at least two concrete implementation slices after alignment or design, load Compass references/task-memory.xml.</rule>
    <rule
        >Implementation may not start until the task memory outcome is reported as created, resumed, or not-required.</rule>
    <rule
        >When task memory is required, docs/.tasks/&lt;task&gt;/goal.md, diagram.md, and memories.md must exist before the first implementation edit or command.</rule>
    <rule
        >Missing docs/_templates task memory files are a documentation gap, not permission to skip this gate.</rule>
  </task-memory-gate>

  <workflow type="new_feature">
    <description>Add a new capability through three gated phases.</description>
    <enforcement>
      <rule
            >Run phases sequentially: brainstorming, then design, then implementation.</rule>
      <rule>Execute exactly one feature per new_feature workflow.</rule>
      <rule
            >If the user's request contains multiple features, create a TODO plan that lists all feature slices, select only one slice for the current workflow, and leave the rest pending.</rule>
      <rule
            >Do not implement multiple features in one new_feature cycle, even when they belong to the same module or share adapters.</rule>
      <rule
            >Brainstorming and design are planning-only phases; do not edit files, write tests, apply patches, or run implementation commands in those phases.</rule>
      <rule
            >Design must produce a usecase-first contract, domain shape, and behavior-test matrix before implementation is allowed.</rule>
      <rule
            >Implementation must run one small approved slice at a time, then stop for developer validation before the next slice.</rule>
      <rule
            >Before implementation starts, satisfy the task-memory-gate for any long or risky multi-slice feature.</rule>
      <rule
            >Stop after each developer_approval_required phase and wait for explicit developer approval before loading or executing the next phase.</rule>
      <rule
            >A request to build a feature starts the workflow; it does not approve skipping brainstorming or design.</rule>
      <rule
            >If the developer explicitly asks to skip a phase, state the skipped gate and risk before continuing.</rule>
    </enforcement>
    <phase name="brainstorming" gate="developer_approval_required">
      <purpose
            >Collaborate on the feature idea and produce a shared UX-level understanding before designing code.</purpose>
      <required-docs>
        <doc>AGENTS.md if present</doc>
        <doc>README.md if present</doc>
        <doc>docs/decisions/0001-orientation-lock.md</doc>
        <doc>docs/foundation/engineering-philosophy.md</doc>
        <doc>docs/foundation/architecture-principles.md</doc>
        <doc>docs/foundation/documentation-principles.md</doc>
        <doc>docs/foundation/testing-principles.md</doc>
        <doc>docs/README.md</doc>
        <doc>orientation-linked architecture, foundation, and process docs</doc>
      </required-docs>
      <actions>
        <action
                >Read the required docs and relevant module or decision docs before asking detailed feature questions.</action>
        <action
                >Confirm that architecture and TDD docs are adapted to the selected or detected project language before design begins.</action>
        <action
                >Do not edit files, create tests, run implementation commands, or apply patches in this phase.</action>
        <action
                >Identify whether the request contains more than one feature; if it does, produce a TODO plan and choose only one feature slice for the current workflow.</action>
        <action
                >Restate the user problem, target users, success criteria, and constraints.</action>
        <action
                >Explore ideas according to project principles: start small, clarity over cleverness, one reason to change, protected boundaries, inward dependencies, and cheap verification.</action>
        <action
                >Produce a UX output: user flow, API-facing behavior, screens or states if relevant, happy path, common path, and visible failure states.</action>
        <action
                >Call out scope exclusions and risks before design begins.</action>
      </actions>
      <phase-output>
        <summary>What the agent understands from the brainstorming.</summary>
        <todo-plan
                >When multiple features are detected, list all feature slices and mark only one as selected for the current workflow.</todo-plan>
        <ux-output
                >User-facing or API-facing behavior, flow, and states.</ux-output>
        <principle-fit>How the idea follows the relevant docs.</principle-fit>
        <open-questions>Questions that still affect design.</open-questions>
      </phase-output>
      <pause-prompt>
        <message>Stop and ask the developer to choose the next step.</message>
        <question
                    id="align-context"
                >Should we run align-context before design?</question>
        <question
                    id="continue-design"
                >Should we continue to the design phase?</question>
        <routine id="align-context">
          <purpose
                    >Challenge the shared understanding without relying on another skill.</purpose>
          <instructions>
            <instruction
                        >Interview the developer relentlessly about every aspect of the selected feature plan until there is a shared understanding.</instruction>
            <instruction
                        >Walk down each branch of the design tree and resolve dependencies between decisions one by one.</instruction>
            <instruction>Ask exactly one question at a time.</instruction>
            <instruction
                        >For each question, provide the agent's recommended answer and a short reason.</instruction>
            <instruction
                        >If a question can be answered by exploring the codebase or documentation, explore the codebase or documentation instead of asking the developer.</instruction>
            <instruction
                        >When exploration answers the question, report the evidence and continue to the next unresolved question.</instruction>
            <instruction
                        >Stop when remaining uncertainty no longer affects the selected feature's design, then summarize aligned decisions, open risks, and the next design input.</instruction>
          </instructions>
        </routine>
      </pause-prompt>
    </phase>

    <phase name="design" gate="developer_approval_required">
      <purpose
            >Design the selected feature's usecase, domain shape, and behavior-test coverage before creating adapters.</purpose>
      <required-docs>
        <doc>AGENTS.md if present</doc>
        <doc>README.md if present</doc>
        <doc>docs/decisions/0001-orientation-lock.md</doc>
        <doc>docs/foundation/engineering-philosophy.md</doc>
        <doc>docs/foundation/architecture-principles.md</doc>
        <doc>docs/foundation/testing-principles.md</doc>
        <doc>docs/architecture/README.md</doc>
        <doc>docs/process/implementation-workflow.md</doc>
        <doc>orientation-linked architecture, foundation, and process docs</doc>
        <doc>relevant docs/modules and docs/decisions notes</doc>
      </required-docs>
      <actions>
        <action
                >Read the required docs, orientation-linked docs, and relevant module or decision docs before designing packages, ports, tests, or data flow.</action>
        <action
                >Do not edit files, create tests, run implementation commands, or apply patches in this phase; describe the test design instead.</action>
        <action
                >Design only the selected feature slice. Keep other feature slices in the TODO plan as pending work.</action>
        <action
                >Identify the relevant boundary and whether this is implementation growth inside the existing structure or an architecture change.</action>
        <action
                >Start from the usecase contract: name, intent, input DTO, output DTO, success result, business errors, and consumer-side ports.</action>
        <action
                >Design the domain shape: entities, value objects, invariants, policies, normalization rules, and domain errors owned by this feature.</action>
        <action
                >Create a behavior-test matrix before implementation. Order scenarios from most common happy/common paths to validation failures, duplicates, missing dependencies, external failures, concurrency, permission, cross-module projection risks, and other edge cases relevant to this feature.</action>
        <action
                >For each behavior scenario, specify the cheapest meaningful test level: domain for pure rules, usecase for orchestration, adapter/integration only for boundary mapping or persistence assumptions.</action>
        <action
                >Mark each suggested behavior as selected, rejected, or postponed. Do not leave the behavior list ambiguous.</action>
        <action
                >Challenge the design for gaps until there is no obvious unhandled common or edge behavior. If a gap remains, ask the developer before implementation.</action>
        <action
                >Do not design delivery, persistence, memory, queue, or external adapters beyond the boundary expectations needed by the contract and behavior tests.</action>
      </actions>
      <phase-output>
        <usecase-contract
                >Usecase name, intent, inputs, outputs, business errors, ports, and dependency direction.</usecase-contract>
        <domain-shape
                >Entities, value objects, invariants, policies, normalization rules, and domain errors.</domain-shape>
        <behavior-test-matrix
                >Ordered behavior scenarios from common to edge, with test level and expected result for each scenario.</behavior-test-matrix>
        <behavior-decisions
                >Selected, rejected, and postponed scenarios with rationale.</behavior-decisions>
        <knowledge-gaps
                >Show list of knowledge gaps which not find in hesitant/ambigous/codebase/context (don't show as questions)</knowledge-gaps>
        <docs-impact>Docs or decision notes that must change.</docs-impact>
      </phase-output>
      <pause-prompt>
        <message
                >Stop and ask the developer to approve the design before implementation.</message>
        <question
                    id="add-behavior"
                >Should any behavior scenario be added, removed, selected, rejected, or postponed?</question>
        <question
                    id="continue-implementation"
                >Should we continue to implementation?</question>
      </pause-prompt>
    </phase>

    <phase name="implementation" gate="manual_checkpoint_required">
      <purpose
            >Implement the approved design through small verified slices, stopping for developer validation after each slice.</purpose>
      <required-docs>
        <doc>AGENTS.md if present</doc>
        <doc>README.md if present</doc>
        <doc>docs/decisions/0001-orientation-lock.md</doc>
        <doc>docs/architecture/README.md</doc>
        <doc>docs/process/implementation-workflow.md</doc>
        <doc>docs/foundation/engineering-philosophy.md</doc>
        <doc>docs/foundation/architecture-principles.md</doc>
        <doc>docs/foundation/testing-principles.md</doc>
        <doc>orientation-linked architecture, foundation, and process docs</doc>
        <doc>relevant docs/modules and docs/decisions notes</doc>
      </required-docs>
      <actions>
        <action
                >Read the required docs, orientation-linked docs, and relevant module or decision docs before editing files.</action>
        <action
                >Confirm that brainstorming and design were approved before editing files.</action>
        <action
                >Before the first implementation edit or command, report the task memory outcome: created, resumed, or not-required.</action>
        <action
                >Implement only the selected feature slice from the approved design. Do not opportunistically implement pending TODO feature slices.</action>
        <action
                >Before editing each implementation slice, state the slice name, exact behavior from the approved matrix, files likely to change, and verification to run.</action>
        <action
                >Implement exactly one small slice per prompt. A slice should usually be one of: core behavior test and core code; one application behavior test and orchestration code; one technical adapter; one delivery adapter mapping; one persistence adapter or migration; one wiring change.</action>
        <action
                >After each slice, run only the relevant verification for that slice, then stop and ask the developer for manual validation before continuing.</action>
        <action
                >Do not continue from core behavior into adapters, or from one adapter into another adapter, without developer approval after the checkpoint.</action>
        <action
                >Implement core behavior and application orchestration before adapters unless the approved slice explicitly starts with infrastructure.</action>
        <action
                >Add adapters only when their boundary behavior needs evidence: delivery for request, response, and status mapping; persistence for mapping, query, and schema assumptions; memory for proof-of-concept or focused tests; technical adapters for concrete outside capabilities.</action>
        <action
                >Keep interfaces on the consumer side and contracts narrow.</action>
        <action
                >Keep composition code near the project's existing composition root.</action>
        <action
                >For read-only projections across boundaries, keep the query outside the core and document the schema dependency with tests or migration evidence.</action>
        <action
                >For rules or invariants owned by another boundary, stop and use an explicit contract or revisit the boundary. Do not duplicate another boundary's rule in persistence queries.</action>
        <action
                >Add comments for why, assumptions, business rules, edge cases, or non-obvious decisions. Do not add mechanical comments.</action>
        <action
                >Run the formatter and tests discovered from the project or documented by the repository. Use the cheapest sufficient verification, then broaden when risk or scope warrants it.</action>
      </actions>
      <phase-output>
        <current-slice>Slice implemented in this prompt.</current-slice>
        <changed-files>Files changed.</changed-files>
        <verification>Commands run and results.</verification>
        <not-run>Verification not run and why.</not-run>
        <remaining-risk>Known gaps or follow-up work.</remaining-risk>
        <next-slice-question
                >Ask whether the developer approves continuing to the next implementation slice.</next-slice-question>
      </phase-output>
    </phase>
    <evidence
        >Approved brainstorming output, approved contract and test design, failing-then-passing behavior test where practical, adapter evidence when adapters are added, touched-scope tests, docs update if contract or boundary changes.</evidence>
  </workflow>

  <workflow type="feature_update">
    <description>Change an existing use case or rule by controlling the delta from protected baseline behavior.</description>
    <enforcement>
      <rule>Run phases sequentially: baseline-discovery, delta-design, implementation-checkpoints, and rollout-cleanup when rollout guards or compatibility paths are introduced.</rule>
      <rule>Classify as architecture_change first when the update changes dependency direction, layer ownership, module structure, or cross-boundary contracts.</rule>
      <rule>Before implementation starts, satisfy the task-memory-gate for any long, risky, or multi-slice update.</rule>
      <rule>Keep core behavior independent of delivery, persistence, framework, and runtime infrastructure.</rule>
      <rule>High-risk updates must define rollback, feature-flag, dark-launch, compatibility, or cleanup evidence before implementation.</rule>
    </enforcement>
    <phase name="baseline-discovery" gate="developer_approval_required">
      <purpose>Protect the current use case, contract, and regression surface before deciding what may change.</purpose>
      <actions>
        <action>Find the owning core rule, application use case, adapter, tests, docs, commands, and composition points.</action>
        <action>State current behavior, public API or delivery contracts, persistence assumptions, external integrations, and expectations that must remain stable.</action>
        <action>Classify update risk as minor, medium, or high based on blast radius, reversibility, data impact, user visibility, and boundary impact.</action>
        <action>Record ambiguity before designing the delta.</action>
      </actions>
      <phase-output>
        <baseline>Owning core/application/adapter behavior, tests, docs, and verification commands observed.</baseline>
        <preserve-list>Behavior, contracts, invariants, and non-goals that must not drift.</preserve-list>
        <risk-level>minor, medium, or high with reason.</risk-level>
        <ambiguity>Conflicts or unknowns.</ambiguity>
      </phase-output>
    </phase>
    <phase name="delta-design" gate="developer_approval_required">
      <purpose>Define the exact behavior change and the cheapest meaningful regression evidence before editing.</purpose>
      <actions>
        <action>State old behavior, new behavior, unchanged behavior, and intentionally removed behavior if any.</action>
        <action>Define core, application, adapter, integration, or end-to-end tests for preserved and changed behavior at the cheapest sufficient level.</action>
        <action>Define the smallest owning layer, module, use case, or adapter to change.</action>
        <action>Decide whether the update needs a feature flag, dark launch, compatibility path, rollback plan, monitoring, docs update, or decision record.</action>
        <action>Define the implementation slices and verification command for each slice.</action>
      </actions>
      <phase-output>
        <delta>Approved behavior change and unchanged behavior.</delta>
        <tests>Regression and changed-behavior test plan.</tests>
        <slices>Ordered implementation checkpoints.</slices>
        <rollout-risk>Flag, rollback, monitoring, compatibility, cleanup, or not needed.</rollout-risk>
        <docs-impact>Docs or decisions to update, or none.</docs-impact>
      </phase-output>
    </phase>
    <phase name="implementation-checkpoints" gate="manual_checkpoint_required">
      <purpose>Apply one approved delta slice while keeping protected behavior covered.</purpose>
      <actions>
        <action>Before the first implementation edit or command, report the task memory outcome: created, resumed, or not-required.</action>
        <action>Add or update the approved regression and changed-behavior tests for the current slice when practical.</action>
        <action>Change the smallest owning core, application, adapter, or composition point and avoid introducing competing patterns.</action>
        <action>Run the current slice verification command.</action>
        <action>Stop after each verified slice and ask before continuing.</action>
      </actions>
      <phase-output>
        <current-slice>Delta slice implemented.</current-slice>
        <baseline-protection>Regression evidence added or reused.</baseline-protection>
        <changed-files>Files changed.</changed-files>
        <verification>Commands run and results.</verification>
        <remaining-risk>Known gaps or follow-up work.</remaining-risk>
      </phase-output>
    </phase>
    <phase name="rollout-cleanup" gate="manual_checkpoint_required">
      <purpose>Close temporary risk controls introduced for the update.</purpose>
      <actions>
        <action>Record feature flag, dark launch, compatibility path, monitoring, rollback, or cleanup status when any were introduced.</action>
        <action>Remove stale flags or inactive compatibility paths after the update is fully accepted.</action>
        <action>Update docs, decisions, public contracts, or runbooks when behavior or rollout expectations changed.</action>
        <action>Run final verification for the touched scope.</action>
      </actions>
      <phase-output>
        <rollout-state>Flag, rollout, compatibility, rollback, or cleanup state.</rollout-state>
        <docs-updated>Docs changed or intentionally unchanged.</docs-updated>
        <verification>Commands run and results.</verification>
      </phase-output>
    </phase>
    <evidence
        >Approved baseline, approved delta design, regression coverage for preserved behavior, changed-behavior verification, slice checkpoints, and rollout or cleanup evidence when needed.</evidence>
  </workflow>

  <workflow type="bug_fix">
    <steps>
      <step order="1">Reproduce or gather evidence for the bug.</step>
      <step order="2">Minimize the failing scenario.</step>
      <step order="3">Identify root cause before editing.</step>
      <step order="4">Add a failing regression test.</step>
      <step order="5">Fix the smallest cause.</step>
      <step
                order="6"
            >Run targeted tests, then broader tests if risk warrants.</step>
    </steps>
    <evidence
        >Reproduction, regression test, and passing verification.</evidence>
  </workflow>

  <workflow type="hotfix_incident">
    <steps>
      <step order="1">Stabilize first and reduce blast radius.</step>
      <step order="2">Identify the smallest safe fix.</step>
      <step order="3">Avoid broad refactors.</step>
      <step order="4">Verify the production-risk path.</step>
      <step
                order="5"
            >Record follow-up work for root cause, tests, and cleanup.</step>
    </steps>
    <evidence
        >Incident symptom addressed, minimal patch verified, follow-up noted.</evidence>
  </workflow>

  <workflow type="refactor">
    <steps>
      <step order="1">Define behavior that must remain unchanged.</step>
      <step order="2">Ensure tests cover the behavior before editing.</step>
      <step order="3">Refactor in small steps.</step>
      <step order="4">Run the same tests after each meaningful step.</step>
      <step order="5">Do not mix behavior changes into the refactor.</step>
    </steps>
    <evidence>Same behavior tests pass before and after.</evidence>
  </workflow>

  <workflow type="architecture_change">
    <steps>
      <step order="1">Read current architecture and decision docs.</step>
      <step order="2">State the boundary or dependency change explicitly.</step>
      <step order="3">Compare 2-3 approaches and trade-offs.</step>
      <step
                order="4"
            >Update architecture or decision docs before or with code.</step>
      <step order="5">Implement in small slices.</step>
      <step order="6">Verify dependency direction and tests.</step>
    </steps>
    <evidence>Updated docs, tests, and dependency-boundary review.</evidence>
  </workflow>

  <workflow type="performance">
    <steps>
      <step order="1">Establish baseline metric.</step>
      <step order="2">Identify bottleneck with evidence.</step>
      <step order="3">Optimize the narrow bottleneck.</step>
      <step order="4">Compare before and after.</step>
      <step order="5">Add benchmark or regression guard when practical.</step>
    </steps>
    <evidence>Measured improvement and no behavior regression.</evidence>
  </workflow>

  <workflow type="security">
    <steps>
      <step order="1">Identify asset, threat, and affected boundary.</step>
      <step
                order="2"
            >Avoid exposing secrets or sensitive data in logs, diffs, or final output.</step>
      <step order="3">Patch the smallest vulnerable path.</step>
      <step
                order="4"
            >Add tests for authorization, validation, sanitization, or failure mode.</step>
      <step order="5">Consider dependency advisories if relevant.</step>
    </steps>
    <evidence
        >Vulnerability path closed, sensitive data protected, tests pass.</evidence>
  </workflow>

  <workflow type="db_migration">
    <steps>
      <step order="1">Identify schema owner and data ownership.</step>
      <step
                order="2"
            >Decide whether the migration is additive, destructive, or data-moving.</step>
      <step order="3">Create migration under the owner scope.</step>
      <step order="4">Define rollback or forward-fix expectations.</step>
      <step
                order="5"
            >Add integration tests for schema assumptions or query behavior.</step>
      <step
                order="6"
            >Ensure cross-boundary read projections are explicit when present.</step>
    </steps>
    <evidence
        >Migration path, rollback or forward plan, integration test or schema check.</evidence>
  </workflow>

  <workflow type="dependency_update">
    <steps>
      <step order="1">Read changelog or release notes when meaningful.</step>
      <step order="2">Identify compatibility risks.</step>
      <step order="3">Update dependency and lockfiles together.</step>
      <step order="4">Run tests and build commands.</step>
      <step
                order="5"
            >Note manual follow-up if behavior changes are required.</step>
    </steps>
    <evidence
        >Updated dependency files and compatibility verification.</evidence>
  </workflow>

  <workflow type="build_ci_tooling">
    <steps>
      <step order="1">Reproduce the current command or CI behavior.</step>
      <step order="2">Change the smallest config or script.</step>
      <step order="3">Run the exact command locally when possible.</step>
      <step
                order="4"
            >Document new command expectations if developer-facing.</step>
    </steps>
    <evidence>Command output or reason it could not be run.</evidence>
  </workflow>

  <workflow type="docs_only">
    <steps>
      <step order="1">Find the source-of-truth document.</step>
      <step order="2">Update the smallest relevant docs.</step>
      <step order="3">Avoid competing sources of truth.</step>
      <step order="4">Verify links, paths, taxonomy, and status.</step>
    </steps>
    <evidence>Changed files and docs verification.</evidence>
  </workflow>

  <workflow type="test_only">
    <steps>
      <step order="1">State the risk the test protects.</step>
      <step
                order="2"
            >Add focused tests without changing production behavior.</step>
      <step
                order="3"
            >Avoid overfitting tests to private implementation details.</step>
      <step order="4">Run targeted tests.</step>
    </steps>
    <evidence>Test command and unchanged production behavior.</evidence>
  </workflow>

  <workflow type="cleanup_chore">
    <steps>
      <step order="1">Keep scope narrow.</step>
      <step
                order="2"
            >Avoid behavior, architecture, and unrelated formatting drift.</step>
      <step order="3">Run the cheapest verification.</step>
    </steps>
    <evidence>Small diff and relevant check.</evidence>
  </workflow>

  <workflow type="research_spike">
    <steps>
      <step order="1">Timebox the investigation.</step>
      <step
                order="2"
            >Gather evidence from code, docs, internet or primary sources.</step>
      <step order="3">Compare options.</step>
      <step order="4">Recommend next action.</step>
      <step order="5">Avoid production code changes unless the user asks.</step>
    </steps>
    <evidence>Findings, options, recommendation, and open questions.</evidence>
  </workflow>

  <workflow type="release_deploy">
    <steps>
      <step order="1">Check branch status and release prerequisites.</step>
      <step order="2">Verify tests, build, and package commands.</step>
      <step
                order="3"
            >Prepare changelog, version, tag, or deploy steps as requested.</step>
      <step
                order="4"
            >Avoid force-push or destructive release actions without explicit approval.</step>
    </steps>
    <evidence>Release checklist and command results.</evidence>
  </workflow>
</workflows-reference>
